How to better practice and feel the guitar
1. Introduction
Hi, it's Dan! Today I'm going to show you how to feel the guitar better.
In any case, I will modestly try to convey to you the way I see things.
Acquire this exercise, because it is an exercise that I will suggest to you,
this will allow us, I think, to be more mentally available to acquire the movements
that we have to acquire when we practice, because I think that quite often,
one of the obstacles to progressing is that you are not really present when you practice and
so we will not create enough, we will not anchor the grooves of the
connections in our brains, I will say like that, which will allow our brain, precisely,
to reproduce these movements mechanically and therefore I think that being more mentally available
when you practice, it will really make the series more effective and efficient
exercises and we will achieve what we want more quickly. I also think that having
awareness of the tensions that we have in the body will allow us to better feel the guitar of
better feel the pressure that we are going to put. And so we will succeed, I imagine to exercise the
just pressure, no tension, no hurting yourself no hurting yourself, and I think it's all gonna be a lot
more fluid. I'll try to explain that to you right away. I suggest you, if you have your instrument not
not keep it with you but put it next to it because we won't need it to begin with.
2. Mindfulness
So these exercises are inspired by mindfulness exercises, initiation to the technique
of mindfulness meditation that I was taught by my instructors that I have
had the chance to meet in Charleroi during an eight-week initiation cycle. And
therefore, I greet them in passing since most likely I am only applying
what they teach me to my sauce, I will say, to better feel and try
to play the guitar better. I think it can apply to all instruments
and I am even convinced that many instrumentalists will perhaps do it
without realizing it or without putting the word "feeling" or "meditation", or whatever ...
it is likely that the fact that I brought up these topics made you a little skeptical
I invite you to try not to think too much and really to try to practice what I
will offer you in time making your own opinion and I also invite you to tell me in
comments, if you decide to do it and experiment, share with me your
feel and see if after a week where you will exercise this every day if you will see
a difference in his guitar playing or whatever instrument you play.
3. Be present
The first exercise I suggest you do, that I suggest you do before starting to practice
the instrument is first of all to sit down. It will sound simple,
Trust me, give it a try, and tell me what you think. It's gonna be to sit down, try to keep your back straight
his head as if it was pulled towards a wire towards the ceiling. You can put your hands on
your legs or not, to the side. So just what I suggest you do is inspire.
To breathe in air, simply and every time you breathe out, try to release
abdominals and make sure that, to really feel gravity, let's say, and that
with each exhalation the weight of your body, I will not say "weigh even more" because it is not
the goal of falling asleep, but in any case the goal is to release the tensions so I will do it and
then I invite you and try to do it and feel it. I breathe in ... and on the exhale
I try to completely relax the abs and possibly the whole body, but I
do not know why, I need before practicing the guitar to relax the abdominals
You can do this, obviously repeat it several times
[inspired]
[expire]
On the exhale, relax the abdominals, all the parts of the body of which you are gradually aware. Repeat as much as you want.
4.Release tensions
Second exercise before practicing the instrument: I invite you to take your left or right arm
whatever, we're gonna do both. Take the left arm, hold it with the right arm
and support the left arm but try to relax it as much as possible for
a few moments while inhaling, exhaling, but the important thing will be to try
to release all control, all muscle impulses in the left arm.
I'm gonna do this for a few moments, really trying not to influence anymore
really, no arm or shoulder muscles and trying to really
completely release the left arm. Once I have done this for a few moments I will
put my hands back like this, and I will try to see if there is a difference between the
left arm and right arm. In theory there should be a difference.
I will do the same but with the right arm and hold it with the left arm.
I try to relax my right arm as much as possible, to hold it
with the left arm, without raising it, simply
keep at the same level and just completely release the right arm. As far as I can
When I did that, when I decide it's ok, I put my hands back like that and
I try, again, to realize if there is a difference or not.
5.the right pressure
Last little exercise which is intended exclusively for guitarists this time. I will suggest you to
tackle a chord or note. We can take a C (C) or the C chord (C chord)
but I found myself by experience and by rubbing shoulders with guitarists that very often what goes
cause that we are going to have pain or that we will not be able to assimilate a complicated fingering,
we are going to have trouble reproducing it, it will be the tension we are going to put on.
We're going to be tense, we're going to have thoughts, we're going to say to each other I can't do it and the thoughts combined
to the bodily tensions are going to make that we will not be in good disposition for really
acquire the movement as efficiently as possible and therefore what I suggest you after
these exercises, it is for example a Do (C chord) and try to exert the right pressure
until it sounds, do not press too hard with the finger of the left or right hand
if you are left-handed and then release until it no longer sounds. Or in any case more
properly. If it doesn't sound right anymore, I'll apply light pressure
until it rings. The goal of this exercise is to find the right pressure. To not
press too hard. Not to hurt your fingers too much or risk having tendonitis
hurt in the long run. After an hour of concert if you exert too much pressure you can
possibly injure yourself not being able to play for three weeks, a month or even two
or three months for the most serious injuries, or more. And so it's important as much as
can be done, whether during an exercise or during a concert or other,
to exert the right pressure at all times. And so that's what we're practicing here for. I invite you
to do that with, whatever the chord, but to do that ... You can also do a barre chord.
And try to find the right pressure until it rings. So if you are a beginner, maybe you will tend to place
your finger in the middle of the fret. Of course it is necessary, instead of pressing harder, it is better to press
less hard and bring your finger to the fret to give yourself as little trouble as possible
And so try, with the left hand to bring ... To acquire the right
pressure I also invite you to try to reproduce this exercise daily before
to start training and share your remarks and findings with me.
Does it change something in your game by doing everyday? Does this
brings a different feeling? Are you going to play better or not? Does that to you
speak ? Doesn't that speak to you? In any case, I invite you to let me know in
comments. Please feel free to click "Like" on this video and share it if you find it interesting.
Eventually subscribing to support me I'm sure that will help me. Thank you, ciao!